Guide to the Marita Sturken Papers, 1958 - 1987 MSS.209
Marita Sturken Papers
1958-1987
MSS.209
Fales Library
0.4 Linear feet
The Marita Sturken Papers consist of original research and secondary source materials accumulated by Sturken in the course of writing three articles on the early history of video art for Afterimage magazine in the 1980s.
Sturken, Marita, 1957-
Separated Materials note
Selected printed materials have been removed and individually catalogued in the Downtown Collection. Records for these items can be retrieved through Bobcat.
1990 Maya Deren Awards for Independent Film and Video Artists, The 1990
1ere Semaine Internationale de Video 1985
9th Atlanta Film and Video Festival 1985
3e Semaine Internationale de Video 1989
A Report on the Television Laboratory at WNET/Thirteen 1978
Abstract Painting 1960-69 1982
Access, Film and Video Equipment: A Directory 1978
Alternating Currents 1978
American Federation of Arts Film Program, The 1984
American Film Institute Video Festival Oct 22-25 1987
American Museum of the Moving Image March 1-May 31, 1989
Art Journal Vol. 45 No. 3 1985
Art Journal Vol. 54 No. 4 1995
Audience 0.01 1991
B.A.C.A. Video Fest 1982
Beyond Video: Media Alliance Directory 1 1984
Biennial Exhibition 1983
Bill Viola 1987
Bill Viola: Arc Musee d'Art Moderne de la Ville de Paris Dec 20 1983-Jan 29 1984
Black Film, British Cinema 1988
Cahiers Du Cinema Supplement to no. 328 Dec 20 1983-Jan 29 1984
Circulating Video Library 1983
Circulating Video Library v.2 1990
Documentary Video: Decades of Change 1986
Eigenwelt Der Apparate-Welt: Pioneers of Electronic Art, Ars Electronica 1992
Electronic Arts Intermix Catalog 1975
Electronic Arts Intermix Catalog 1976
Electronic Arts Intermix Catalog 1977-78
Electronic Arts Intermix Catalog 1982
Felix Vol. 1, No. 2 1992
Felix Vol. 2, No. 1 1995
Forum de Arte Contemporanea June 1989
From Media to Metaphor: Art About AIDS 1991
From the Academy of the Avant Garde 1981
From the Academy to the Avant Garde 1981
From TV to Video Dec 20 1983-Jan 29 1984
Heresies Vol 25: The Art of Education 1990
Heresies Vol 4, No. 4, Issue 16: Film Video 1983
Heresies Vol 6, no. 4 Issue 24: 12 Years 1989
High Performance # 56 Winter 1991
Home Made Movies: 20 Years of American 8 MM and Super-8 Films May 1-June 30, 1981
ICC Biennale '97: Communication/Discommunication 1997
Independent, The v. 9, no. 3 Apr-86
IS Journal v. 2, no. 1 1987
IS Journal v. 2, no. 2 1987
Japanese Experimental Film 1960-1980 1981
Joan Jonas, Scripts and Descriptions 1968-1982 1983
Kitchen/Video no date
Masterpieces of Moving Image Technology Sep. 10, 1988
Media Arts in Transition, The June 8 - 11 1983
Media Arts Magazine v. 1, No. 9 Spring/Summer 1985
Mostra de Video Norte-Americano Nov. 1989
Media Arts Magazine v. 2, No. 7 Spring/Summer 1990
Muntadas Exhibition May 1-31, 1987 1987
National Video Festival June 10-13 1982 and June 24-27, 1982
National Video Festival September 22-25 1983 and October 22-23 1983
National Video Festival September 20-23 1984
National Video Festival September 19-22 1985
New American Filmmakers 1976
New Feminist Research v.19, no. 2 June 1990
New Internationalist No. 185 July 1988
New Langton Arts Catalog of Programs 1988
New Video: Japan 1985
Paper Tiger Guide to TV Repair, The 1992
Paper Tiger Television Catalog 1993-94
Paper Tiger Television Catalog no date
Performance Text(e)s and Documents 1981
Re/Search 1991
Resolution: A Critique of Video Art 1986
Roar! Paper Tiger Television 1991
Scratching the Belly of the Beast: Cutting-Edge Media in Los Angeles, 1922-94 Film Forum. 1994
Set in Motion 1994
Shigeko Kubota June 19-Aug 25, 1996
Siggraph '83 Exhibition of Computer Art July 25-29 1983
Spheres D'Influence de Tony Oursler 1986
Steina and Woody Vasulka: Fahnrenheit 451 1995
Steina and Woody Vasulka: Machine Media 1993
Steina and Woody Vasulka: Machine Media July 25-29 1983
Steina and Woody Vasulka: Videastes 1984
Time and Memory: Video Art and Identity July 25-29 1983
TV Guides: A Collection of Thoughts about Television 1985
TV Magazine V. 1, No. 1 Spring 1983
Vasulka 1978
Video Art and Alternative Media in the United States Oct 23- Nov 23, 1997
Video Art: Expanded Forms 1988
Video By Artists 2 1986
Video Networks v. 16, no. 5 Oct/Nov 1992
Video Tape Review 1986
Video Texts: 1983 1983
Video: A Retrospective 1984
West Vol. 1, no. 1 1989
Woody Vasulka: The Brotherhood 1998
American Museum of the Moving Image Shikego Kubota Video Sculpture 1991
Brown, Wendy Deregulating Women: The Trials of Freedom Under a Thousand Points of Light. Subversions Winter 1999
Chapkis, Wendy Suggestive Language; On Sex Workers and (Other) Feminists. Subversions. Winter 1991
Goldberg, Roselee Performance: Live Art 1909 to the Present 1979
Goodeve, Thyrza Female Man, The: Hysterical Jerry Professes Desire Winter 1991
Hanhardt, John G. Nam June Paik 1982
Hart, Ellen Louise Encoding of Homoerotic Desire: Emily Dickinson's Letters and Poems to Susan Dickinson 1850-1886. Subversions Winter 1991
Indianapolis Museum of Art Muntadas, Words: The Press Conference Room 1991
Judson, William et al. American Landscape Video: The Electronic Grove 1988
Kruger, Barbara ed. TV Guides: A Collection of Thoughts about Television 1985
Leong, Russel Moving the Image: Independent Asian Pacific American Media Arts 1991
Lucier, Mary Wilderness Jan. 12-Feb. 16 1986
McClintic, Miranda Directions 1981 1981
Magnan, Nathalie Le Video Entre Art et Communication 1997
Marin, Lynda Mother and Child: The Erotic Bond. Subversions. Winter 1992
Marsh, Ken Independent Video 1974
Niemann, Linda Gender Roles in Cornfield Meet: A Study of Women Railroaders on the Southern Pacific. Subversions. Winter 1991
Paik, Nam June et al. Fluxus/Video 1983
Payant, Rene, ed. Video 1986
Salz, Kay Film Service Profiles 1980
Vijande, Fernando, ed. Muntadas: Exposition 1985
Walter Phillips Gallery, Banff Centre School of Fine Arts Second Link, The: Viewpoints on Video in the Eighties 1983
Wilde, Edy and Gary Schwartz Luminous Image, The. Het Lumineuze Beeld 1984
Wilson, Robert Theater of Images, The 1974
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Provenance
The materials were donated to the Fales Library and Special Collections by Marita Sturken in March of 2008.
Biographical note
Marita Sturken is Professor of Culture and Communication and Co-Director of the Visual Culture Program at New York University's Steinhardt School of Culture, Education, and Human Development, where she teaches courses on cultural studies, popular culture, advertising, and global culture. Before coming to NYU she was an Associate Professor at the Annenberg School for Communication at the University of Southern California, and worked as a critic in independent film and video. She is author of Tourists of History: Memory, Kitsch, and Consumerism from Oklahoma City to Ground Zero (2007) and Tangled Memories: The Vietnam War, the AIDS Epidemic, and the Politics of Remembering (1997), and Co-Author of Practices of Looking: An Introduction to Visual Culture (2001).While working as a critic in the 1980s she wrote a series of articles for Afterimage magazine documenting the early history of video art and community video.
Scope and Content note
The Marita Sturken Papers are a part of the Downtown Collection at the Fales Library, New York University. The Fales Library is the primary special collections division of the NYU libraries, housing nearly 200,000 volumes of English and American literature from 1700 to the present. Strengths of the collection include the development of the English and American novel, with an emphasis on the Gothic and the Victorian novel. The Downtown Collection, of which the Marita Sturken Papers are a part, is a comprehensive collection of printed materials, archives, and other materials related to the Downtown New York scene from ca. 1975 to the present.
This collection is made up of original research and secondary source materials accumulated by Sturken while writing three articles about the early history of video and electronic arts for Afterimage magazine. The articles are "An Interview with George Stoney" (January 1984), "TV as a Creative Medium: Howard Wise and Video Art" (June 1984) and "Howard Klein and the Rockefeller Foundation's Funding of the Media Arts" (January 1987). The first two articles were part of a series on video art funded by the New York State Council on the Arts Media Program. The collection consists of three subseries, representing the research generated for each article. The materials include correspondence, handwritten research notes, typed transcripts of interviews, original gallery catalogs, and photocopies of exhibition catalogs, gallery announcements, newspaper articles and magazine articles.
Arrangement note
Following the order of the original materials, the collection is organized into one series (Research Materials) and three subseries. Each subseries represents the research for a single article for Afterimage magazine. Folders are organized within subseries in alphabetical order, and the materials within folders are in chronological order.
Access Points
Subject Names:
Klein, Howard; Paik, Nam June; Stoney, George C.; Sturken, Marita, 1957 -; Wise, Howard
Subject Organizations:
Electronic Arts Intermix (organization)
Subject Topics:
Video Art
- Series I: Research Materials
  - Subseries A: Howard Wise Gallery
    - Articles, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Articles, 1969 - 1970 and undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Charlotte Moorman Playing Opera Sextronique by Nam June Paik" flyer, February 9, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "EAI Video News" Video Newsletter, August 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Electronic Arts Intermix, Inc - at the Leading Edge of Art" pamphlet, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Howard Wise Gallery Press Releases (photocopies), 1965-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Howard Wise photocopied exhibition catalogs, 1958-1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Light, Motion, Space" photocopied exhibition catalog, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Lights in Orbit" exhibition catalog, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Luminism" exhibition announcement mailing, May 25, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Press releases (not Wise Gallery), 1968 and undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "TV as a Creative Medium" exhibition announcement mailing, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Uecker - Howard Wise Gallery" exhibition catalog, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Vision and Television" photocopied exhibition catalog, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subseries B: Howard Klein
    - Articles, 1965, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Interview transcripts: Nam June Paik, Russell Connor, David Loxton, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Howard Klein interview transcript, March 27, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Newsletters, pamphlet, 1983, 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Newspaper articles re. Rockefeller grants, 1971 - 1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Research notes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Research notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - List of Rockefeller Grants in Televeision, Video, Film, 1965-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Subseries C: George C. Stoney
    - Research materials - George Stoney, 1971 - 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)